Register of the Ferenc Marosy Papers, 1948-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
Ferenc Marosy Papers,
1948-1981
79042
Marosy, Ferenc, 1893-1986
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, speeches and writings, and clippings, relating to anti-communist Hungarian emigre activities, Hungarians in Spain, and political conditions in Spain.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Anti-communist movements.; Communism.; Hungarians--Spain.; Hungary.; Spain.; Spain--Politics and government--1939-1975.
Biographical Notes
(Francis Mengele de Maros-Solymos before 1936)
also known as Francis de Marosy
1893 June 30 born Szeged, Hungary
1911-1915 attended the University of Budapest (Péter Pázmány University).
1915-1918 Lieutenant, Austro-Hungarian Armed Forces, Artillery.
1919 Diplomatic Attache, Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Budapest.
1924-1926 Secretary, Hungarian Legation, Bucharest, Romania.
1929 Author of A Népszövetség jogi és politikai rendszere. (Legal and political system of the League of Nations), Budapest, Franklin, 1929
1930-1932 Secretary and Charge d'Affaires, Hungarian Legation, Madrid, Spain.
1933-1936 Press Chief, Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Budapest.
1936 Membership awarded in the Hungarian "Vitéz Order" and changed his last name from "Mengele" to "Marosy."
1937-1939 Councillor and Charge d'Affaires, Hungarian Legation, London, England.
1939-1940 Consul General, Hungarian Consulate, Prague, Czecho-Slovakia.
1941 Charge d'Affaires, Hungarian Legation, Cairo, Egypt.
1941-1943 Minister Plenipotentiary, Hungarian Legation, Zagreb, Croatia.
1944 May Minister Plenipotentiary, Hungarian Legation, Helsinki, Finland.
1944 October Dissident and exiled in Stockholm, Sweden.
1946-1948 Exiled in Madrid, Spain.
1949-1969 Representative of Hungarian National Council, New York, N.Y., semiofficially accredited as Free Hungarian Minister, Hungarian Legation, Madrid, Spain.
1969-1979 Delegate of European Free Hungarian Congress, Madrid, Spain.
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1967 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- WRITINGS, 1954. (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
- REPORTS, 1948-1969. (Box 1)
  Political reports to Magyar Nemzeti Bizottmány (Hungarian National Committee), and to Free Europe Committee; Quarterly political reports to H.R.H. Otto von Habsburg and to Europai Szabad Magyar Kongresszus (European Free Hungarian Congress), arranged chronologically.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1948-1967
  - Artajo, Albert Martin (Madrid, Spain), 1955 (Box 1)
  - Bessenyey, Gyoergy, Baron (New York, N.Y.). 1948-1958
  - Castiella, Don Fernando Maria de (Madrid, Spain), November 23, 1958
  - Eckhárdt, Tibor (New York, N.Y.), August 21, 1957
  - Hammarskjold, Dag (New York, N.Y.), December 22, 1960
  - Hory, András (Wien, Austria), May 3, 1963
  - Hungarian Committee (New York, N.Y.), 1953 (8 letters) 1966 (1 letter)
  - Ku Cheng-kang (Madrid, Spain), February 1957, (2 letters)
  - Lodge, John David (Madrid, Spain), 1960-1961, (2 letters)
  - Macartney, C.A. (Edingburgh, Scottland), January 1959
  - Mindszenty, József, Cardinal (Madrid, Spain) April 1, 1967, (2 letters)
  - Navarro, Don Carlos Arias (Madrid, Spain), April 1, 1960
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1954.
  - "A középeurópai ujjáépités elvi alapjai," (Basic principles of the Central European reconstruction), radio speech, Radio Madrid, Tudósító (Reporter), June 25, 1954, 196 sz. Printed copy. (Box 1)
  - "The Madrid Hungarian Legation and her services to the cause of Liberation," carbon copy typescript, n.d.
  - "La solidarité européenne mise a l'epreuve. Politique de principes ou politique de réalités?" carbon copy typescript, n.d.
- REPORTS, 1948-1969
  - Hungary. Követség (Legation, Spain). Political reports to Magyar Nemzeti Bizottmány (Hungarian National Committee, New York, N.Y.), 1948-1958 (Box 1)
  - Hungary. Követség (Legation, Spain). Political reports to Free Europe Committee, 1955-1960.
  - Hungary. Követség (Legation, Spain). Quarterly political reports to H.R.H. Otto von Habsburg, and Europai Szabad Magyar Kongresszus (European Free Hungarian Congress), 1959-1969.